Guide to the Records of The New York Institute for the Humanities RG.37.4
New York University Archives
- Series III. Audio and Video Recordings, 1974-2010
  - Subseries IIIB. 1/4 Inch Reels, 1976-1991
    - Future of the Intellectual Community Conference I, December 11, 1976; cuid4249; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 1)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:39)
    - Future of the Intellectual Community Conference II, December 11, 1976; cuid4250; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 2)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:40)
    - James Lecture: Richard Wollheim "On Persons and Their Lives" I, September 29, 1977; cuid4251; Wollheim, Richard, 1923-2003; Approx. 32 minutes
      Inauguration of the James Lectures. British philosopher Richard Wollheim discusses the relationship of philosophy and psychology in his lecture "On Persons and Their Lives." Good audio.
      tape reels; Psychology and philosophy; Audiotapes.
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 3)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:11)
    - James Lecture: Richard Wollheim "On Persons and Their Lives" II, September 29, 1977; cuid4252; Wollheim, Richard, 1923-2003; Approx. 32 minutes
      Psychology and philosophy; tape reels; Audiotapes.
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 4)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:12)
    - James Lecture: Wollheim "On Person and Their Lives" III, September 29, 1977; cuid4253; Wollheim, Richard, 1923-2003; 1 sound tape reels Approx. 8 minutes
      Psychology and philosophy
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 5)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:13)
    - James Lecture: Wollheim "On Persons and Their Lives" I, 29-Sept-77; cuid4254 (Box 73, Folder 6)
    - James Lecture: Wollheim "On Persons and Their Lives" II, 29-Sept-77; cuid4255 (Box 73, Folder 7)
    - James Lecture: Wollheim "On Persons and Their Lives", 29-Sept-77; cuid4256 (Box 73, Folder 8)
    - James Lecture: Susan Sontag "Illness as a Metaphor" I Master, October 13, 1977; cuid4257; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; Approx. 33 minutes
      Susan Sontag lectures on a topic that would become the title of her non-fiction work the following year, Illness as Metaphor.
      Tuberculosis; Cancer; tape reels; Audiotapes.
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 9)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:8)
    - James Lecture: Susan Sontag "Illness as a Metaphor" II Master, October 13, 1977; cuid4258; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; Approx. 32 minutes
      Susan Sontag lectures on a topic that would become the title of her non-fiction work the following year, Illness as Metaphor. Good Audio.
      Tuberculosis; Cancer; Audiotapes.; tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 10)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:9)
    - James Lecture: Susan Sontag "Illness as a Metaphor" III Master, October 13, 1977; cuid4259; Sontag, Susan, 1933-2004; Approx. 19 minutes
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 11)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:10)
    - James Lecture: Susan Sontag "Illness as a Metaphor" I Copy, 13-Oct-77; cuid4260 (Box 73, Folder 12)
    - James Lecture: Susan Sontag "Illness as a Metaphor" II Copy, 13-Oct-77; cuid4261 (Box 73, Folder 13)
    - James Lecture: Susan Sontag "Illness as a Metaphor" III Copy, 13-Oct-77; cuid4262 (Box 73, Folder 14)
    - Rationalization and Civilization I Master, March 16, 1978; cuid4263; 1 sound tape reels; Box label: RATIONALIZATION & CIVILIZATION, 3/16/78, I, 3 3/4 IPS Master, R. Sennett, H. Gintis, C. Offe, T. Schoyer
      3-3/4 IPS.
      Offe, Claus; Schroyer, Trent; Gintis, Herbert; Sennett, Richard, 1943-
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 27)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:25)
    - Rationalization and Civilization II Master, March 16, 1978; cuid4264; 1 sound tape reels; Box label: RATIONALIZATION & CIVILIZATION, 3/16/78, II, 3 3/4 IPS Master, R. Sennett, H. Gintis, C. Offe, T. Schoyer
      3 3/4 IPS
      Gintis, Herbert; Schroyer, Trent; Sennett, Richard, 1943-; Offe, Claus
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 23)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:26)
    - Rationalization and Civilization I Master, March 17, 1978; cuid4265; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 15)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:27)
    - Rationalization and Civilization II Master, March 17, 1978; cuid4266; 1 sound tape reels; Label: RATIONALIZATION & CIVILIZATION, 3/18/78, II, 3 3/4 IPS Master
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 16)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:28)
    - Rationalization and Civilization III Master, March 17, 1978; cuid4267; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 17)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:29)
    - Rationalization and Civilization IV Master, March 17, 1978; cuid4268; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 18)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:30)
    - Rationalization and Civilization V Master, March 17, 1978; cuid4269; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 19)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:31)
    - Rationalization and Civilization I Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4270; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 22)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:32)
    - Rationalization and Civilization II Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4271; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 28)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:33)
    - Rationalization and Civilization III Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4272; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 24)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:34)
    - Rationalization and Civilization IV Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4273; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 25)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:35)
    - Rationalization and Civilization V Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4274; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 26)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:36)
    - Rationalization and Civilization VI Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4275; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 20)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:37)
    - Rationalization and Civilization VII Master, March 18, 1978; cuid4276; 1 sound tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 21)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:38)
    - "Memory in Romantic Song Cycles" A James Lecture by Charles Rosen, October 26, 1978; RG37.4-JL-30; Rosen, Charles, 1927-2012; 1 sound tape reels Approx. 80 minutes
      First lecture in the James Lecture series for fall semester, 1978. American concert pianist and music writer Charles Rosen delivers a lecture entitled "Memory in Romantic Song Cycles." He discusses landscape imagery as a setting of both permanence and change, in paintings, poetry, and musical composition. Q&A at 01:14:10.
      tape reels; Audiotapes.; Song cycles; Landscapes.; Memory; Schumann, Robert, 1810-1856 -- History
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 29)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:14)
    - "Biography and Creativity" A James Lecture by Roland Barthes, November 6, 1978; RG37.4-JL-31; Approx. 70 minutes
      Roland Barthes lectures in French on "Biography and Creativity"Before introducing Barthes, the "chair of the James lectures" mentions that Paul Ricœur, who was scheduled to lecture the following week had had a heart attack in Chicago and would be unable to give his talk. Ricœur came back to speak the following year.
      tape reels; Audiotapes.; Barthes, Roland
      - Original Recording (Box 73, Quarter inch audio reel 30)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:15)
    - "Marxism: For and Against" a Gallatin Lecture by Robert L. Heilbroner, February 8, 1979; cuid4277; 1 sound tape reels Approx 90 minutes
      Part of the Spring 1979 Gallatin lecture Series, Robert Heilbroner argues for and against Marxism. Introduced by Tom Bender.
      Marxism -- History.; Heilbroner, Robert L.; Bender, Thomas, 1944-
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 1)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:11-9:12)
    - "Democracy and 'The Competition of Ideas'" a Gallatin Lecture by Charles E. Lindblom, February 22, 1979; cuid4278; 2 sound tape reels Approx. 98 minutes; The first reel has 96 minutes of content. The second reel was used only to record the very end of the Q&A session and is only 2 minutes 11 seconds long.
      This event was recorded on two reels of tape. These reels were initially described as individual entities before being combined as one. The Unique Identifier of the first reel was ref2415. Both are now included as ref2416.
      Introduced by Thomas Bender, economist, political scientist and professor of economics and political science at Yale University Charles E. Lindblom delivers the second lecture in the Spring 1979 Gallatin Lecture series. The lecture is entitled Democracy and "The Competition of Ideas," subtitled "How much competition and what kind?" Q&A session after lecture (around the 65th minute) lasts for about a half hour.
      Recorded on (2) 1/4" tape reels at 3 3/4 IPS.
      Political science.; Democracy; Economics.; Bender, Thomas, 1944-; Lindblom, Charles E., 1917-2018
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 3)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:29-9:31)
    - "The Sacred and the Body Social in Sixteenth Century Lyon" a Gallatin Lecture by Natalie Zemon Davis, March 18, 1979; cuid4279; 1 sound tape reels Approx. 90 minutes
      Part of the Spring 1979 Gallatin Lecture series, Natalie Zemon Davis discusses life in sixtenth century Lyon. Introduced by Tom Bender.
      Lyon (France); Bender, Thomas, 1944-; Davis, Natalie Zemon, 1928-
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 4)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:13-9:14)
    - "John Dewey and the Kingdoms of Light" a Gallatin Lecture by Quentin Anderson, March 22, 1979; cuid4280; 1 sound tape reels Approx. 77 minutes
      The final lecture in the Spring 1979 Gallatin Lecture series. Columbia University Professor in the Humanities, Quentin Anderson, best known for his work The Imperial Self, turns his sights to "John Dewey and the Kingdoms of Light." Introduced by Tom Bender.
      Anderson, Quentin, 1912-2003; Dewey, John, 1859-1952; Bender, Thomas, 1944-
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 5)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:15)
    - Readings and Discussion of Recent Work. A James Lecture by V.S. Naipul, April 24, 1979; cuid4281; Naipaul, V. S. (Vidiadhar Surajprasad), 1932-2018; Approx. 75 minutes
      Nobel Laureate author V. S. Naipul reads four pieces of his work, explaining and describing the selections as he goes.
      Selections read: 1. "Jasmine" - story published in Times literary supplement in 1964. - about the act of reading and writing in colonial Trinidad. 2. Excerpt from In A Free State. 3. One Out of Many - about an Indian servant brought to Washington by his employer. 4. Excerpt from A Bend In The River
      No Q&A
      Audiotapes.; tape reels; Naipaul, V. S. (Vidiadhar Surajprasad), 1932- Bend in the river.
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 6)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:24)
    - "Occult Philosophy in the Elizabethan Age" -- A James Lecture by Dame Frances Yates, May 8, 1979; cuid4282; Yates, Frances Amelia; Approx. 75 minutes
      Renaissance historian, Dame Frances Yates delivers lecture entitled, "Occult Philosophy in the Elizabethan Age."
      Good audio.
      No Q&A.
      Occultism; Elizabethan; tape reels; occult; Audiotapes.; occult sciences
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 7)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:23)
    - "The Origins of Universal History in Greece and Rome," a Humanities Council Lecture by Dr. Arnaldo Momigliano, May 15, 1979; cuid4283; Approx. 70 minutes
      Emminent historian and professor of history at University of London and University of Chicago, Arnaldo Momigliano, delivers a lecture on the origins of universal history in Greece and Rome, touching on many early writers, philosophers, and historians.
      Roman history; Greek history; Rome; Historiography.; Momigliano, Arnaldo
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 8)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:26)
    - "Body Consciousness and the Modern Writer" A James Lecture by Jean Starobinski, May 22, 1979; cuid4284; Starobinski, Jean; Approx. 65 minutes
      Jean Starobinski, "one of the leading humanist scholars of Western Europe," lectures on "Body Consciousness and the Modern Writer."
      Good Audio.
      Somesthesia; tape reels; Audiotapes.
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 9)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:3)
    - Film as False Sociology Symposium, October 13, 1979; cuid4285; 2 sound tape reels Approx. 2.5 hours
      The thesis put forth for this small symposium is that Film is a type of false sociology. Panelists are invited to speak on that topic, either supporting or refuting the statement. Stanley Cavell, who helped organize the event was unable to attend because of an illness in his family. Present panel members include film critic, author and Johns Hopkins Professor of English Leo Braudy, and novelist and screenwriter Joe Eszterhas.
      This event was recorded on two reels of tape. These reels were initially described as individual entities before being combined as one. The Unique Identifier of the second reel was ref2450. Both are now included as ref2449.
      Film.; Sociology.; Film criticism.; Cavell, Stanley, 1926-; Eszterhas, Joe; Braudy, Leo
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 13)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:16-9:18)
    - "What Should Intellectuals Do?" A James Lecture by Theodore Zeldin, November 6, 1979; cuid4286; Zeldin, Theodore, 1933-; Approx. 58 minutes
      French historian, Theodore Zeldin gives "counter-disciplinary" lecture on how intellectuals view themselves and possible alternative definitions and roles.
      Good audio. Q&A begins at 48:30. Questions are distant from mic, quiet but audible.
      Audiotapes.; tape reels
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 15)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:4)
    - "Is History Still Narrative?" A James Lecture by Paul Ricouer, November 15, 1979; cuid4287; Ricœur, Paul; Approx. 62 minutes
      French professor of Philosphy Paul Ricœur lectures on the role of narrative form in historical writing.
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 16)
      - Access Copy (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:5)
    - "Contemporary German Poetry" A Ross Institute Conference with Discussion and Readings by Hans Magnus Enzensberger, November 27, 1978; cuid4288; 1 sound tape reels Approx. 82 minutes; Container label: ROSS INSTITUTE CONFERENCE 11/27/78 III
      It is unclear what the roman numeral III on the container label "ROSS INSTITUTE CONFERENCE 11/27/78 III" is supposed to indicate - whether the third Ross Institute Conference of the semester, the third event with Hans Magnus Enzensberger, or the third reel from this particular conference, because there are no other materials present that would help identify a series.
      Hans Magnus Enzensberger reads a number of his own poems (in English and German) and engages in a discussion on contemporary German poetry and the atmosphere of the country and other influences on contemporary German poetry. Readings are interspersed with explanations of the work. There is a Q&A session at the end.
      The recording starts with about two minutes of the host instructing people to gather closer together along with the sounds of scuffling chairs and general motion, followed by a five minute introduction of Enzensberger.
      Epic poetry, German; German poetry -- 20th century; German poetry; Poetry.; Enzensberger, Hans Magnus
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 17)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:27-9:28)
    - Bronx Developmental Center Panel Discussion: Session I of the Architecture of Confinement Symposium, November 28, 1979; cuid4289; 2 sound tape reels Approx. 2 hours, 6 minutes
      This is the first of two panel discussions in the Architecture of Confinement Syposium. The second may be found in this series (Box 74, folder 21).
      This is the first session of the Symposium on the Architecture of Confinement. The topic of discussion is the Bronx Developmental Center. Introduced by Tom Bender, each of the panelists speaks on the subject, followed by general discussion. The first speaker and moderator of the panel is David Rothman, professor of history at Columbia University, who gives historical background on the topic being discussed. Second is Dr. Herbert Cohen, professor of pediatrics and rehabilitative medicine at Albert Einstein College of Medicine and the Director of the Bronx Developmental Center. The third panelist is Chris Hansen, a lawyer with the New York Chapter of the ACLU who acted as a key litigator in NYSARC v. Carey (the Willowbrook case), which had a significant impact on the care of intellectually disabled people and influenced the design of the Bronx Developmental Center. Fourth is Richard Myer, the architect who designed the Bronx Developmental Center. Finally, the last panelist is Arthur Drexler, curator of architecture at the Museum of Modern Art.
      This event was recorded on two reels of tape. The second reel was previously thought to be a separate intellectual entity and given its own unique identifier: ref2377. The preservation master for that tape is labeled as such.
      3-3/4 IPS
      Developmental psychology; Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York.; Architecture |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Architecture; Bender, Thomas, 1944-; Willowbrook State School; Drexler, Arthur; Meier, Richard, 1934-; Cohen, Herbert Jesse, 1935-; American Civil Liberties Union; Hansen, Chris; Bronx Developmental Center; New York Civil Liberties Union; Staten Island Developmental Center; Bronx State Developmental Center
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 18)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:32-9:33)
    - Metropolitan Correctional Center Panel Discussion: Session II of the Architecture of Confinement Symposium, December 12, 1979; cuid4290; 2 sound tape reels Approx 1 hour, 50 minutes
      This event was recorded on two reels of 1/4" tape. These reels were initially described as individual entities before being combined as one. The Unique Identifier of the second reel was ref2379. Both are now included in ref2378.
      Introduced by Tom Bender, this second session of the Architecture of Confinement Symposium focused on the Metropolitan Correctional Center a federal administrative detention facility opened in 1975, located in lower Manhattan. As with the first session, each of the panelists speaks on the subject, followed by general discussion. The participants are listed below in the order in which they spoke.
      Former ACLU director and fellow of New York Institute for the Humanities Aryeh Neier speaks first and acts as moderator. Paul Silver, the architect of the Metropolitan Correctional Center speaks next. Silver is followed by Alvin J. Bronstein, the founder and director of the National Prison Project. After Bronstein is Judge Morris Lasker, a federal district judge who was in the litigation concerning conditions in the Tombs. The last panelist to speak is Kenneth Schoen, a program office at the Edna McConnell Clark Foundation, who is speaking more from his role as the former Corrections Commissioner of Minnesota.
      This is the second of two panel discussions in the Architecture of Confinement Syposium. The first may be found in this series (Box 74, folder 18).
      Prisons.; Imprisonment; Architecture -- New York (State) -- New York.; Architecture |z United States |x History |y 20th century.; Architecture; Construction and architecture.; Bender, Thomas, 1944-; Neier, Aryeh, 1937-; Schoen, Kenneth; Lasker, Morris E.; Edna McConnell Clark Foundation; Minnesota. Department of Corrections; Manhattan Detention Complex (New York, N.Y.); Halls of Justice (New York, N.Y.); United States. Bureau of Prisons; Bronstein, Alvin J.
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 21)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 112, Cd 9:44-9:46)
    - A James Lecture by Joseph Brodsky, November 21, 1979; cuid4291; Brodsky, Joseph, 1940-1996; Approx. 90 minutes
      Russian American poet & essayist, Joseph Brodsky gives an untitled lecture that the introducer says will demonstrate why Brodsky had said "Not all James lectures are alike." Brodsky speaks mostly in Russian. Barry Rubin, a lecturer in the Slavic Languages department at Queens College reads Brodsky's poems in English, throughout the lecture.
      Audiotapes.; tape reels; Russian American Poetry
      - Original Recording (Box 74, Quarter inch audio reel 20)
      - Access Copies (Box Shared University Archives 107, Cd 2:16A-2:16B)
    - The Act of Censoring: Session I of the Censorship and Writers Conference, February 1, 1980; cuid4292; 2 sound tape reels Approximately 2 hours
      Recording of the introduction to and the first session of the Writers and Censorship Conference hosted by the New York Institute for the Humanities on February 1-2, 1980. This first session took place on the evening of February 1, is lead by Bob Silvers and Aryeh Neier and deals with the act of censoring, itself. Richard Sennet introduces the theme of the conference (described below) and welcomes the leaders of the first session.
      This conference focuses on the question "What does censorship do in terms of the act of writing?" The premise of this two day conference is the complicated relationship between writer and censor and between writing and censorship. This involves discussion on how the two are not necessarily diametrically opposed. Questions of complicity between the two are explored, looking at how the writer may serve as his own censor, creating a grey area between the act of expression and the act of repression. Rather than formal presentations, each session was started by one or two people "put some ideas on the table" and then a general discussion among the participants.